Columbia River Treaty audio collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Columbia River Treaty audio collection
2011-2015
2009
1996
1974
F-227
Q105668565
13 cm of textual records 14 sound recordings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
published
Full
Revised
Title based on contents of the collection.
Includes 14 audio reels (originals), 27 audio cassettes (copies), and 32 DVDs (copies).
Collection consists of records available in multiple formats relating to the 14-lecture series "Canadian-American Relations: Perspectives on the Columbia River Treaty" held at Simon Fraser University in 1974.
The Columbia River Treaty was an agreement between Canada and the United States for flood control and the construction of dams for the generation of hydroelectricity. Four dams were constructed - three in Canada (Mica, Arrow, and Duncan) and one in the United States (Libby). The treaty was signed in 1961 but was not ratified by the Canadian Parliament. The treaty was so controversial that a Protocol was drawn up, which eventually defined the monetary terms and operational procedures without changing any of the physical plan. The Protocol was agreed upon in 1964.
The lecture series was organized through the combined efforts of the Canadian Studies Program, the Department of Continuing Studies, and the Alumni Association and was chaired by Professor George Cook of the History Department. Each lecture was given by a person who had been closely connected to the Columbia River Treaty. Admission to attend the lectures was free. All lectures were held in the East Concourse Cafeteria, SFU (Burnaby campus).
Collection consists of audio recordings of the Columbia River Treaty lecture series advertised by Simon Fraser University as "a series of talks and panels designed to increase public understanding of this issue in Canadian-American relations on the international, national, regional and local levels and from the political, legal, economic, geographic and social aspects." The collection also consists of transcripts compiled by BC Hydro (Dania Robinson) in 2011 from the audio recordings of the Columbia River Treaty lecture series. Due to variable audio quality, the transcripts are not a full disclosure of the lectures. Researchers are advised to review access copies of the original audio recordings.
Document types include reel to reel, audio cassette tapes, digital (mp3 format) as well as transcripts (paper and PDF formats) of the audio recordings.
Collection was originally arranged as a listing of sound recordings. With the donation of the transcripts, the collection was arranged into two series, with separate series for audio recordings (F-227-1) and transcripts (F-227-2). In 2015, the digitized sound recordings and born-digital transcripts were ingested into Archivematica and DIPs were delivered to Atom. The series were collapsed into files once more.
BC Hydro; Cook, George; Sound recordings; Textual records; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital); Environment; Government; Natural resources; Transportation and utilities
Audio reels were transferred to the Archives from the SFU Audio Visual Centre. In 1996 copies of the audio reels were made to audio cassette for reference purposes. In 2009 digital copies were made from the audio cassettes. Transcripts of the lectures were created by BC Hydro and donated to the Archives in 2011 (series 2).
As of November 2011, all accessions have been processed. Corrected transcripts from BC Hydro are expected.
For records relating to hydroelectricity and the Columbia River Treaty, please see the finding aid for the W.A.C. Bennett fonds (F-55). The Archives holds two other collections relating to two of the speakers for this lecture series: see the James W. Wilson regional planning collection (F-132); and the Hugh Keenleyside interview collection (F-137).
For published material on the treaty, please see the book "The Sociology of Natural Resources" by John Elliott (published in 1981 by Butterworth & Co. (Canada) Ltd.) which contains a chapter entitled "The Columbia River Treaty: Growth Versus Development and the Implications."
The records in this collection are open with no restrictions.
- Title page, table of contents and disclaimer to transcripts of Columbia River Treaty SFU Lectures, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  published
  Textual records
  Open
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-1
  - Title Page
  - Index-Disclaimer
- Lecture 1 Howard Green and Dr. Cook: The Columbia River Treaty 1963: the Background and the Negotiations, January 1974; F-227-0-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Green, Howard C.; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-2
  - Lecture 1: audio recording, January 30, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-2-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2758, Audio cassette OBJ-2828, Audio cassette OBJ-2829, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2855, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2856, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2857)
    Lecture given by Hon. Howard C. Green, Secretary of State for External Affairs, 1959-1963.
    Green, Howard C.; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item1, F-227-item2, F-227-item28, F-227-item42, F-227-item43, F-227-1-0-0-2.
    - Lecture 1: audio recording, part 1
      Sound recordings
    - Lecture 1: audio recording, part 2
  - Lecture 1: transcription, 2011, 2015; F-227-0-0-0-2-2
- Lecture 2 Alvin Hamilton, Chairman, Columbia River Liaison Committee, 1 February 1974; F-227-0-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Hamilton, Alvin; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-3
  - Lecture 2: audio recording, February 1, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-3-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2759, Audio cassette OBJ-2830, Audio cassette OBJ-2831, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2858, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2859)
    Lecture given by Hon. Alvin Hamilton, Minister of Northern Affairs and Natural Resources, 1957-1960. Hamilton was the Chairman of The Columbia River Liaison Committee.
    Hamilton, Alvin; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item3, F-227-item4, F-227-item29, F-227-item44, F-227-item45, F-227-1-0-0-2.
    - CRT2HamiltonAv1
    - CRT2HamiltonAv2
    - CRT2HamiltonAv3
  - Lecture 2: transcription (revised), F-227-0-0-0-3-2
- Lecture 3 Arthur Laing, Minister of Northern Affairs, Senator, 6 February 1974; F-227-0-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Laing, Arthur; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-4
  - Lecture 3: transcription
  - Lecture 3: audio recording, February 8, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-4-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2760, Audio cassette OBJ-2832, Audio cassette OBJ-2833, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2860, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2861)
    Lecture given by Hon. Senator Arthur Laing, Minister of Northern Affairs and Natural Resources, 1963-1966.
    Laing, Arthur; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item5, F-227-item6, F-227-item30, F-227-item46, F-227-item47, F-227-1-0-0-3.
    - CRT3LaingAv1
    - CRT3LaingAv2
- Lecture 4 Gordon Shrum, President, BC Hydro, 20 February 1974; F-227-0-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Shrum, Gordon; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-5
  - Lecture 4: transcription, F-227-0-0-0-5-2
  - Lecture 4: audio recording, February 20, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-5-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2761, Audio cassette OBJ-2834, Audio cassette OBJ-2835, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2862, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2863)
    Lecture given by Gordon M. Shrum, Chairman, B.C. Energy Board, 1960-1972; Co-Chairman, B.C. Hydro and Power Authority, 1962-1972.
    Shrum, Gordon; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item7, F-227-item8, F-227-item31, F-227-item48, F-227-item49, F-227-1-0-0-4.
    - CRT4ShrumGv1
    - CRT4ShrumGv2
- Lecture 5 Bob Strachan, Leader, New Democratic Party, 22 February 1974; F-227-0-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Strachan, Bob; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-6
  - CRT Lecture 5
  - Lecture 5: audio recording, February 22, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-6-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2762, Audio cassette OBJ-2836, Audio cassette OBJ-2837, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2864, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2865)
    Lecture given by Bob Strachan, Leader of the British Columbia New Democratic Party; BC Leader of the Opposition, 1956-1969.
    Strachan, Bob; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item9, F-227-item10, F-227-item32, F-227-item50, F-227-item51, F-227-1-0-0-5.
    - CRT5StrachanBv1
    - CRT5StrachanBv2
- Lecture 6 Neil Swainson, UVic Political Science Professor, 27 February 1974; F-227-0-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Swainson, Neil; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-7
  - CRT lecture 6
  - Lecture 6 - Neil Swainson: Fact, Fancy and Lessons Related to the Columbia River Treaty Experience, February 27, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-7-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2763, Audio cassette OBJ-2838, Audio cassette OBJ-2839, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2866, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2867, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2868)
    Lecture given by Dr. Neil Swainson, Political Scientist, Westwater Research Centre.
    Swainson, Neil; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item13, F-227-item14, F-227-item33, F-227-item52, F-227-item53, F-227-1-0-0-6.
    - CRT6SwainsonNv1
    - CRT6SwainsonNv2
    - CRT6SwainsonNv3
- Lecture 7 Larat Higgins, Technical Advisor, 1 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Higgins, Larat; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-8
  - CRT Lecture 7
  - Lecture 7 Larrett Higgins: The Columbia River Treaty: Aftermath and Policy Implications, March 1, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-8-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2764, Audio cassette OBJ-2840, Audio cassette OBJ-2841, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2869, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2870)
    Lecture given by Larrat T. Higgins, Economist, Ontario Hydro Commission.
    Higgins, Larat; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item15, F-227-item16, F-227-item34, F-227-item54, F-227-item55, F-227-1-0-0-7.
    - CRT7HigginsLv1
    - CRT7HigginsLv2
- Lecture 8 Jim Wilson, Executive Director, BC Hydro, 8 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Wilson, James W.; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-9
  - CRT Lecture 8
  - Lecture 8 Jim Wilson: The Human Aspects of the Columbia River Treaty, March 13, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-9-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2765, Audio cassette OBJ-2842, Audio cassette OBJ-2843, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2871, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2872)
    Lecture given by Jim W. Wilson, Executive Director, B.C. Hydro and Power Authority. Author of "People in the Way".
    Wilson, James W.; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item17, F-227-item18, F-227-item35, F-227-item56, F-227-item57, F-227-1-0-0-8.
    - CRT8WilsonJv1
    - CRT8WilsonJv2
- Lecture 9 Ian McDougall, Environmental Lawyer, 13 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  McDougall, Ian; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-10
  - CRT Lecture 9
  - Lecture 9 Ian McDougall: The Lesson of the Columbia River Treaty as applied to Joint Energy Development, March 15, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-10-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2766, Audio cassette OBJ-2844, Audio cassette OBJ-2845, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2873, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2874)
    Lecture given by Professor Ian McDougall, Faculty of Law, Dalhousie University.
    McDougall, Ian; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item19, F-227-item20, F-227-item36, F-227-item58, F-227-item59, F-227-1-0-0-10.
    - CRT9McDougallIv1
    - CRT9McDougallIv2
- Lecture 10 Marian Marts, U.S. Professor of Environmental Geography, 15 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Marts, Marion; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-11
  - CRT Lecture 10
  - Lecture 10 Marion Marts: Retrospection on the Great River Treaty from South of the Border, March 22, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-11-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2768, Audio cassette OBJ-2848, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2878, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2879)
    Item consists of the taped lecture given by Professor Marion Marts, Professor of Geography, University of Washington.
    Marts, Marion; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item23, F-227-item38, F-227-item62, F-227-1-0-0-10.
    - CRT10MartsMv1
    - CRT10MartsMv2
- Lecture 11 Ray Williston, Minister of Lands, Forests and Water Resources, 20 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Williston, Ray; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-12
  - CRT Lecture 11
  - Lecture 11 Ray Williston: The Position of the Government of BC in the Columbia River Treaty Negotiations, March 20, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-12-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2767, Audio cassette OBJ-2846, Audio cassette OBJ-2847, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2875, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2876, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2877)
    Item consists of the taped lecture given by Ray Williston, Minister of Lands, Forests and Water Resources for B.C., 1966-1972.
    Williston, Ray; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item21, F-227-item22, F-227-item37, F-227-item60, F-227-item61, F-227-1-0-0-11.
    - CRT11WillistonRv1
    - CRT11WillistonRv2
    - CRT11WillistonRv3
- Lecture 12 Charles Bourne, UBC Law Professor, 22 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Bourne, Charles; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-13
  - Lecture 12 Charles Bourne: Legal Issues in the Settlement of the Columbia River Treaty Dispute, March 27, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-13-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2769, Audio cassette OBJ-2849, Audio cassette OBJ-2850, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2880, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2881)
    Lecture given by Professor Charles F. Bourne, faculty of Law, University of British Columbia.
    Bourne, Charles; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item24, F-227-item25, F-227-item39, F-227-item66, F-227-item67, F-227-1-0-0-12.
    - CRT12BourneCv1
    - CRT12BourneCv2
    - CRT12BourneCv3
  - CRT Lecture 12
- Lecture 13 Gordon MacNabb, Senior ADM, Energy Mines and Resources, 27 March 1974; F-227-0-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  MacNabb, Gordon; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  Previously numbered as F-227-2-0-0-14
  - CRT Lecture 13
  - CRT Lecture 13 Second Revision Dec 2015
  - Lecture 13 Gordon MacNabb: Columbia River Treaty, April 2, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-14-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2770, Audio cassette OBJ-2851, Audio cassette OBJ-2852, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2882, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2883, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2884)
    Lecture given by Gordon MacNabb, senior engineering adviser to the Canadian federal government during the negotiation of the Columbia River Treaty.
    McNabb, Gordon; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item26, F-227-item27, F-227-item40, F-227-item64, F-227-item65, F-227-1-0-0-13.
    - CRT13MacNabGv1
    - CRT13MacNabGv2
    - CRT13MacNabGv3
- Lecture 14 Hugh Keenleyside, Chairmain, BC Hydro, 3 April 1974; F-227-0-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 227-4, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2887)
  Keenleyside, Hugh; Textual records; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized); Records in electronic form (born-digital)
  - CRT Lecture 14
  - Lecture 14 Hugh Keenleyside: The Development of the Columbia River, April 3, 1974; F-227-0-0-0-15-1 (Audio reel OBJ-2771, Audio cassette OBJ-2853, Audio cassette OBJ-2854, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2885, Optical disc: dvd OBJ-2886)
    Lecture given by Hugh L. Keenleyside, Chairman, B.C. Power Commission, 1959-1962; Co-Chairman, B.C. Hydro & Power Authority, 1962-1969.
    Keenleyside, Hugh; Sound recordings
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-227-item11, F-227-item12, F-227-item41, F-227-item68, F-227-item69, F-227-1-0-0-14.
    - CRT14KeenleysideHv1
    - CRT14KeenleysideHv2